Preliminary Guide to the Henry R. Lang Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Roseman Lang papers
1723-1934
1880-1934
MS 937
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12.75
Correspondence, diaries and appointment books, and writings and notes, which reflect Henry Roseman Lang's career as professor of Romance Languages and Literature at Yale. The papers also contain correspondence, diaries, addresses books, and notes of his wife, Alice Derby Lang.
Lang, Henry Roseman, 1853-1934
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Henry R. Lang estate, 1935.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Henry R. Lang Papers consist of nine linear feet of correspondence, diaries and appointment books, and writings and notes pertaining to his academic interests plus correspondence, notes and other materials of his wife, Alice Derby Lang (d. 1928).
Lang's writings, note and research materials specifically concern Spanish, Portuguese and Italian poetry; these follow his correspondence and diaries, etc., and are in no definite arrangement.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Roseman Lang was born in Wartau, Switzerland, on September 22, 1853. He received a Ph.D. from the University of Strassberg in 1890. Within two years, he moved to New Haven, Connecticut and began teaching at Yale University, where he stayed for the rest of his career. Between 1892 and 1893, he was instructor in Romance languages, then assistant professor of Romance Philology until 1896, followed by professor of Romance Philology until 1906, when he became the Benjamin F. Barge Professor of Romance Language and Literature, a position he held until his retirement in 1922, when he became professor emeritus. He died in 1934.
Literature -- History and criticism; Portuguese language -- Lexicography; Portuguese poetry; Spanish language -- Lexicography; Diaries; Educators; Lang, Alice Derby; Lang, Henry Roseman, 1853-1934; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Henry R. Lang
    - Correspondence
      - 1880-1907 (Box 1)
      - 1908-1924 (Box 2)
      - 1925-1934 (Box 3)
    - Diaries, address books, appointment books, receipts, 1890-1934 (Box 4–5)
    - Lectures, writings, notes, research materials, 1881, 1933, undated (Box 6–14)
    - Photostats of manuscripts in Spanish, undated (Box 15–16)
    - Notes on Spanish lexicography, undated (Box 17–22)
    - Notes on Portuguese lexicography, undated (Box 23–24)
    - Notes on Portuguese lyric poetry, undated (Box 25)
    - Legal document in Spanish and Latin, 1723 (Box 26)
    - Certificates of membership conferred on Henry R. Lang by various institutions, 1893-1927 (Box 26)
    - Ph.D. diploma, 1892 (Box 30)
  - Alice Hubbard (Derby) Lang
    - Correspondence, diaries, address books, notes, 1896-1928, undated (Box 27–29)